Guide to the Will Irwin and Inez Haynes Gillmore Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Will Irwin and Inez Haynes Gillmore papers
1887-1961
1904-1961
YCAL MSS 603
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.92
(33 boxes)
The collection consists primarly of correspondence and diaries, as well as a small amount of writings, photographs, and clippings, documenting the life and work of Inez Haynes Irwin and Will Irwin.
Irwin, Will, 1873-1948
Gillmore, Inez Haynes, 1873-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Eben Given, 1964. Gift of Jane Parker, 1981.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Will Irwin (1873-1948)
Will Irwin, American journalist and author. Irwin was born September 14, 1873, in Oneida, New York. He received a B.A. from Stanford University in 1899. He worked for a number of years as a newspaper report at the San Francisco Wave, the San Francisco Chronicle and the New York Sun, and then for a year as a writing editor at McClure's in 1906.
Irwin then spent a number of years as a free-lance journalist and fiction writer. In 1915 he went abroad as a war correspondent and covered World War I action for both British and American periodicals. Following several years of observing and reporting on the war, Irwin returned to the United States in 1920. He thereafter wrote numerous anti-war publications, among them his best-selling book The Next War (1921). His other books include Christ or Mars? (1923), Herbert Hoover: A Reminiscent Biography (1928), Propaganda and the News; or, What Makes You Think So? (1936), his autobiographical Making of a Reporter (1942), and The American Newspaper (1969).
Irwin died of cerebral occlusion, February 24, 1948, in Greenwich Village, New York.
"Will(iam) (Henry) Irwin." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2003. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 21 Aug. 2012.
Inez Haynes Gillmore Irwin (1873-1970)
Inez Haynes Irwin, American author and political activist. Haynes Irwin was born March 2, 1873, in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. She attended Radcliffe College from 1897-1900. Haynes Irwin was an ardent supporter of women's suffrage and co-founded the National Collegiate Equal Suffrage League. She was also a member of the National Advisory Council of the National Women's party. Haynes Irwin's book, The Story of the Women's Party, is an account of the history and activities of this political organization.
In her writing, Haynes Irwin confronted the issues of divorce, single-parenthood, unwed motherhood, and women in the work force. Her works include: Phoebe and Ernest (1910), The Lady of Kingdoms (1917), Gertrude Haviland's Divorce (1925), and Angels and Amazons: A Hundred Years of American Women (1933).
Haynes Irwin married Rufus Hamilton Gillmore in 1897; that marriage ended. She married Will Irwin in 1916.
Haynes Irwin died September 25, 1970.
"Inez Haynes Irwin." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2002. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 21 Aug. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarly of correspondence and diaries, as well as a small amount of writings, photographs, and clippings, documenting the life and work of Inez Haynes Irwin and Will Irwin.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1905-1931. II. Diaries, 1917-1961. III. Other Papers, 1887-1945.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Gillmore, Inez Haynes, 1873-1970; Irwin, Will, 1873-1948
- Correspondence, 1905-1931; Series I; 4.96; (11 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters received by Inez Haynes Irwin from Will Irwin.
  - Burgess, Gelett, 1907-1910; 7 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Phyllis Given to her mother Maud Duganne, undated (Box 1)
  - Given, Phyllis, 1914-1927, undated (Box 2)
  - Irwin, Will, 1905-1907 August; 12 (Box 2)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1907 September - 1910 March; 7 (Box 3)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1910 January - 1911 June; 7 (Box 4)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1911 August - 1913 May; 7 (Box 5)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1913 December - 1914 April; 8 (Box 6)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1914 April - June; 7 (Box 7)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1914 August - 1931, undated; 6 (Box 8)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1910-1915, undated; 6 (Box 9)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1908-1910, undated; 8 (Box 10)
  - Irwin, Will (continued), 1906; 2 (Box 11)
- Diaries, 1917-1961; Series II; 7.92; (19 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Inez Haynes Irwin Diaries and Will Irwin Diaries.
  - Inez Haynes Irwin Diaries
    - 1917-1923, 5 (Box 12)
    - 1924-1928, 5 (Box 13)
    - 1929-1931, 3 (Box 14)
    - 1932-1934, 3 (Box 15)
    - 1934-1936, 3 (Box 16)
    - 1937-1938, 2 (Box 17)
    - 1939-1940, 2 (Box 18)
    - 1941-1943, 3 (Box 19)
    - 1944-1946, 3 (Box 20)
    - 1947-1949, 3 (Box 21)
    - 1950-1952, 3 (Box 22)
    - 1954-1956, 3 (Box 23)
    - 1957-1959, 3 (Box 24)
    - 1960-1961, 2 (Box 25)
  - Will Irwin Diaries
    - 1925-1926, 2 (Box 25)
    - 1927-1931, 4 (Box 26)
    - 1932-1935, 4 (Box 27)
    - 1936-1939, 4 (Box 28)
    - 1940-1943, 4 (Box 29)
    - 1944-1947, 4 (Box 30)
- Other Papers, 1887-1945; Series III; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  - "The Hamadryads, A Masque of Apollo in One Act by Will H. Irwin," typescript (Box 31)
  - "Midsummer High Jinks, 1904, The Hamadryads by Will Irwin," photograph album (Box 31)
  - Photograph, Will Irwin (Box 31)
  - Photograph, Inez Haynes Irwin (Box 31)
  - The Sunday Herald, 1923 (Box 31)
  - Will Irwin material
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Jane Parker, 1981.
    - Photograph of Will Irwin, 1930 (Box 32)
    - Letters from Will Irwin to Phyllis Given, 1939-1940, undated (Box 32)
    - Poems written by Will Irwin when he was at Stanford University, typescript, undated (Box 32)
  - Inez Haynes Irwin material
    - Writings by Inez Haynes Irwin, typescripts, undated (Box 33)
    - Spring in Paris, typescript, 1917 (Box 33)
    - Diary of Inez Haynes Irwin on her first visit to Paris, 1908 (Box 33)
    - Correspondence of Inez Haynes Irwin
      - Irwin, Will, undated (Box 33)
      - Given, Phyllis, 1914-1945, undated (Box 33)
      - Given, Phyllis & Maud Duganne, 1917 (Box 33)
      - Given, Eben, 1942 March 16 (Box 33)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 33)
    - Photographs of Inez Haynes Irwin, 1887-1920, undated; 3 (Box 33)